Guide to the Matthew Stadler Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Matthew Stadler papers
1977-2011
GEN MSS 843
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
34.26
(39 boxes) + 3 broadside folders
The collection consists of material stemming from Matthew Stadler's activities as an author, editor, and literary organizer, and includes writings, correspondence, business papers, ephemera, journals, teaching material, computer disks, and three laptop computers.
Stadler, Matthew, 1959-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Matthew Stadler on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2011. Gift of Matthew Stadler, 2011.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 40 (computer disks): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies of electronic files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Box 41-42 (computers and computer disks): Restricted pending accessioning and preliminary processing.
Matthew Stadler
Matthew Stadler was born in Seattle, Washington in 1959, and studied at Oberlin College (B.A.,1981). He is the author of the novels Landscape: Memory (1990), The Dissolution of Nicholas Dee (1992), The Sex Offender: A Moral Tale (1994), Allan Stein (1999), and Chloe Jarren's La Cucaracha (2011), as well as numerous short stories, essays about art, architecture and urbanism, and a book about urban planning, Deventer (2011). He has edited four anthologies of literature and non-fiction, The Clear Cut Future (2003), Core Sample: Portland Art Now (2004); the back room anthology (2006), and Where We Live Now (2008). He was literary editor of Nest magazine from 1996 to 2002 and founding editor of Clear Cut Press from 2001 to 2007.
In addition to writing, Stadler's primary work has been to create new infrastructure for literary culture, especially in the Pacific Northwest region. Among his major projects are: the Rendezvous Room Reading Series in Seattle (1989-1999); the Extension Project teaching program, which became the Richard Hugo House literary arts center, of which Stadler was a founding board member, also in Seattle (1991-); a quarterly book review and books coverage for the newsweekly The Stranger in Seattle (1995-1999); "the back room" literary dinner series in Portland (2004-); and Publication Studio, a print-on-demand literary press in Portland (2009-).
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of material stemming from Matthew Stadler's activities as an author, editor, and literary organizer, and includes writings, correspondence, business papers, ephemera, journals, teaching material, computer disks, and three laptop computers.
Project Files and Editorial Files contain correspondence with many writers and artists, including Lawrence Rinder, Guy Davenport, James Purdy, James Lord, Robert Gluck, John Ashbery, Kenward Elmslie, Michael Silverblatt, Edmund White, and James Kincaid, among others.
Writings consist of notes and drafts for Stadler's novels, Landscape: Memory (1990), The Dissolution of Nicholas Dee (1992), The Sex Offender: A Moral Tale (1994), and Allen Stein (1999). Writings by others can be found amongst the Project Files and Editorial Files and include drafts, edited by Stadler, of works by Eileen Myles, Lydia Davis, James Purdy, Matt Briggs, Diana George, James Kincaid, Stacey Levine, Lisa Robertson, Robert Gluck, Kevin Killian, Alex Ross, D. Lee Williams, Steve Weiner, and Lawrence Rinder, among others.
Ephemera found in the Project Files include hand-made 'zines, posters, letters, cards, and other announcements, reflecting Stadler's punk/DIY roots. Examples include "NoTime magazine," a 1980 cut-up lit/art 'zine made by Stadler and Elizabeth Bouiss; cards and announcements of Stadler's readings (1989-1997); posters for Rendezvous Room Readings (1990-1993); handmade art projects and cards for friends (1977-2010); and issues of Teen Fag and miscellaneous other 'zines relating to Stadler's writing and research.
Electronic files on the laptop computers and computer disks comprise the bulk of Stadler's writing, editing, and correspondence from 1996-2004.
Arrangement
Organized into five series: I. Project Files. II. Writings. III. Editorial Files. IV. Other Papers. V. Computers and Computer Disks.
American literature -- 20th Century; American literature -- 21st century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Authors, American -- 21st century -- Archives; Editors -- United States -- 20th Century; Editors -- United States -- 21st century; Gay authors; Gay men; Homosexuality and literature; Born digital; Electronic documents; Storage devices (computer equipment); Authors -- United States; Editors -- United States; LGBTQ resource; Stadler, Matthew, 1959-
- Project Files, Series I; 12.42; (13 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Files have been maintained in the order in which they were received by the library.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. consists of files relating to a broad range of Matthew Stadler's literary activities and projects.
  - MacArthur Foundation, 3 (Box 1)
  - Household equipment (Box 1)
  - Visual clips (Box 1)
  - Insurance, 2 (Box 1)
  - Holland '88, circa 1988 (Box 1)
  - Calendar '91, 1991 (Box 1)
  - Calendar '92, 1992 (Box 1)
  - Loft $ (empty folder) (Box 1)
  - Bank (Box 1)
  - News by kids (Box 1)
  - Contracts, 2 (Box 1)
  - Extension Project brochures (Box 1)
  - Tom Spanbauer (Box 1)
  - Student loan (Box 1)
  - Rebecca Brown (Box 1)
  - Lynne Tillman (Box 1)
  - Guy Davenport (Box 1)
  - Addresses (Box 1)
  - r³ - Rendevouz Readings Series stationery (Box 1)
  - Alex Ross (Box 1)
  - Dodie Bellamy (Box 1)
  - Dodie Bellamy (continued) (Box 2)
  - Jay Scrivener, 2 (Box 2)
  - Martha Baer (Box 2)
  - Charles Mudede (Box 2)
  - Larry Rinder, 2 (Box 2)
  - Collette Brooks (Box 2)
  - Kevin Killian, 2 (Box 2)
  - Jan Wallace, 2 (Box 2)
  - Bob Gluck (& Fenton) (Box 2)
  - Larmon BIZ (Box 2)
  - Chris Gallagher (Box 2)
  - Stuart Sherman (Box 2)
  - Wooster Group (Box 2)
  - Michael Feingold, 2 (Box 2)
  - Friends: cool writing (Box 2)
  - Re: Alex (Box 2)
  - Jimi Hendrix (Box 3)
  - D. Lee Williams (Box 3)
  - Josh Leibner (Box 3)
  - Meg Richman (Box 3)
  - Chris Jones (Box 3)
  - Epistemology articles (Box 3)
  - Lit. / Theory articles (Box 3)
  - Cartography articles (Box 3)
  - Vierlingh: Dijkage (Box 3)
  - Technology (Box 3)
  - Mohammed Daoudi (Box 3)
  - Denton Welch (Box 3)
  - Lover / Killer (Box 3)
  - Stories: original copies, 3 (Box 3)
  - My big NM fiction (Box 3)
  - Sleep miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous fiction notes (Box 3)
  - Landscape: Memory miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Landscape: Memory graphics (Box 3)
  - X-Country diary '80, circa 1980 (Box 3)
  - Stories: copies (Box 3)
  - My fiction excerpts, 2 (Box 3)
  - NP notes, 2 (Box 4)
  - Book mailing lists (Box 4)
  - My old journalism (Box 4)
  - Academic papers (Box 4)
  - Encyc. project (Box 4)
  - Old interviews (Box 4)
  - Article ideas (Box 4)
  - Writings by Matthew Stadler, 2 (Box 4)
  - Student papers, 4 (Box 4)
  - Laundromat, 2 (Box 4)
  - Purdy article, 2 (Box 4)
  - Purdy article (continued), 2 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous projects (Box 5)
  - Places to write 4 (Box 5)
  - Encyclopedia (Box 5)
  - Books to get (empty folder) (Box 5)
  - Model essays (Box 5)
  - Purdy letters, 2 (Box 5)
  - Purdy event, 2 (Box 5)
  - James Purdy, 3 (Box 5)
  - My fave journalism, 2 (Box 5)
  - Manuscript edits 4 "Yellow Sailor" (Steve Weiner), 3 (Box 5)
  - Short stories (Box 5)
  - My curricula, 2 (Box 6)
  - Nest copy edits (Box 6)
  - My stories (Box 6)
  - Lecture series (Box 6)
  - Nest proposals (Box 6)
  - Centrum (Box 6)
  - Bard (Box 6)
  - Bad writers / Nest (empty folder) (Box 6)
  - Letters to Nest (Box 6)
  - Nest issue # 11 (empty folder) (Box 6)
  - My new Nest art (Box 6)
  - Future Nest stories? (empty folder) (Box 6)
  - Nest articles in progress (empty folder) (Box 6)
  - Nest to do now (Box 6)
  - Career documents (Box 6)
  - Allan photos / documents (Box 6)
  - Boys articles (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous old file (Box 6)
  - Bills (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous, 2 (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous, 2 (Box 7)
    Includes 1 computer disk
    Conditions Governing Access
    Computer disks are restricted. Copies of electronic files may be requested through Access Services: Disk # 2011.genm.43289.0002
  - Allan / France (Box 7)
  - Gertrude / Alice (empty folder) (Box 7)
  - Allan business (Box 7)
  - Allan: boys (Box 7)
  - Stein family letters (Box 7)
  - Allan's letters (Box 7)
  - Allan Stein (Box 7)
  - Allan pages (Box 7)
  - Allan bibliography (Box 7)
  - r³ - Rendezvous Readings Series mailing list (Box 7)
  - To be filed (Box 7)
  - Wiederhall (Box 7)
  - U.S. soccer
  - Theater / Perf. (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
  - Precious manuscripts (Box 7)
  - Loft letters, 2 (Box 7)
  - Vacation fun (empty folder) (Box 8)
  - Family letters, 2 (Box 8)
  - Stadler letters (Box 8)
  - Allan BIZ (Box 8)
  - Zahler letters, 2 (Box 8)
  - Medical (Box 8)
  - Columbia MFA '85, circa 1985; 2 (Box 8)
  - ripe essays (Box 8)
  - Writers' retreats, 2 (Box 8)
  - Voluptuary notes (Box 8)
  - Official papers (Box 8)
  - Official papers (continued) (Box 9)
  - Mail inserts (Box 9)
  - Holland letters, 2 (Box 9)
  - Sex Offender BIZ, 2 (Box 9)
  - Seattle letters, 4 (Box 9)
  - Overseas letters, 2 (Box 9)
  - Agent / Publisher letters (Box 9)
  - Agent / Publisher letters (continued) (Box 10)
  - Oberlin friends letters, 2 (Box 10)
  - USA letters (Box 10)
  - NYC letters, 2 (Box 10)
  - SF / LA letters (Box 10)
  - Grant BIZ letters (Box 10)
  - School business letters (Box 10)
  - ARLVA letters (Box 10)
  - Letters (Box 10)
  - Book-Lit. letters (Box 10)
  - Letters, 2 (Box 10)
  - Letters, 5 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, writings, and other materials (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous short writings, 2 (Box 11)
  - Teaching... Homos (Box 11)
  - Teaching jobs (Box 11)
  - Sonics (Box 11)
  - Mirage # 4 / Period(ical), 6 (Box 11)
  - Mirage # 4 /Period(ical) (continued), 2 (Box 12)
  - Book contracts, 6 (Box 12)
  - Seattle Public Library, 3 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence and other materials, 3 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence and other materials (continued) (Box 13)
  - Rendezvous Readings Series and other projects, 2 (Box 13)
    Computer disks are restricted. Copies of electronic files may be requested through Access Services: Disk # 2011.genm.43289.0005, From How To Create a Cultural District and Have it Vanish Into the Morning Mists of Dawn (a project initiated by Red76); Matthew Stadler reads City of Wool
- Writings, Series II; 8.21; (8 boxes) + 3 folders
  Arranged alphabetically by title at the box level.
  - Allan Stein, circa 1999; 22 (Box 14)
  - Allan Stein, circa 1999; 13 (Box 15)
  - The Dissolution of Nicholas Dee, circa 1992; 14 (Box 15)
  - The Dissolution of Nicholas Dee, circa 1992; 19 (Box 16)
  - The Dissolution of Nicholas Dee, circa 1992; 16 (Box 17)
  - The Dissolution of Nicholas Dee, circa 1992; 5 (Box 18)
  - Landscape: Memory, circa 1990; 12 (Box 18)
  - Landscape: Memory, circa 1990; 5 (Box 19)
  - Sex Offender, circa 1994; 12 (Box 19)
  - Sex Offender, circa 1994; 15 (Box 20)
  - Sex Offender, circa 1994; 4 (Box 21)
  - Sex Offender: Letourneau research, circa 1994; 12 (Box 21)
  - Sex Offender: Letourneau research, circa 1994; 3 (Box 22)
    Includes 1 audiocassette
- Editorial Files, Series III; 7; (6 boxes) + 16 folders
  Organized at the box level into three groups: Clear Cut Press, Nest, and Manuscripts by Others.
  Series III consists of files stemming from Stadler's work as founding editor of Clear Cut Press and literary editor of Nest magazine.
  - Clear Cut Press, 15 (Box 22)
  - Clear Cut Press, 18 (Box 23)
    Computer disks are restricted. Copies of electronic files may be requested through Access Services: Disk # 2011.genm.43289.0004, Clear Cut Future: Final Files
  - Clear Cut Press, 17 (Box 24)
  - Clear Cut Press, 7 (Box 25)
  - Clear Cut Press (Core Sample book)
  - Nest, 9 (Box 25)
  - Nest, 15 (Box 26)
    Computer disks are restricted. Copies of electronic files may be requested through Access Services: Disk # 2011.genm.43289.0003, Nest Disc, 6/29/98
  - Nest, 3 (Box 27)
  - Manuscripts by others, 15 (Box 27)
  - Manuscripts by others, 18 (Box 28)
  - Manuscripts by others (Box 29)
- Other Papers, Series IV; 3.63; (4 boxes)
  Not arranged in any particular order.
  - Journals, 13 (Box 29)
  - Journals, 18 (Box 30)
  - Teaching materials, 3 (Box 30)
  - Teaching materials, 10 (Box 31)
  - Reviews, 5 (Box 31)
  - Career history documents, 2 (Box 32)
  - Printed material (Box 32)
  - La Cucaracha - Printed with annotations, 2 (Box 32)
  - Letter by James Lord (Box 32)
  - Out with the stars by James Purdy (Box 32)
  - Press releases, book covers for Landscape: Memory and Allan Stein (Box 32)
  - The Stranger (Box 32)
  - Miscellaneous writings by Stadler and others, 2 (Box 32)
  - Ron Athy (empty folder) (Box 32)
  - North American Man/Boy Love Association (NAMBLA) (Box 32)
  - Centrum, 3 (Box 32)
  - Wicked Sounds by David Mahler
  - Artwork by James Purdy
- Computers and Computer Disks, Series V
  Restricted pending accessioning and preliminary processing.
  Related Archival Materials note
  A handful of computer disks were also found amongst Project Files and Editorial Files. These are described intellectually in the contents list for Series I and III, respectively.
  - Computers
  - Computer disks
- Oversize Material, 1; (4 boxes)
  - Landscape: Memory graphics (from Series I), circa 1990 (Box 33 Oversize)
  - Nest (from Series I) (Box 33 Oversize)
  - Seattle Public Library (from Series I), 3 (Box 33 Oversize)
  - Correspondence, writings, and other materials (from Series I) (Box 33 Oversize)
  - Centrum (from Series I) (Box 34 Oversize)
  - U.S. Soccer (from Series I) (Box 34 Oversize)
  - Book contracts (from Series I) (Box 34 Oversize)
  - Nest (from Series I) (Box 34 Oversize)
  - Landscape: Memory (from Series II), circa 1990 (Box 34 Oversize)
  - Clear Cut Press (Core Sample book) (from Series III) (Box 35 Oversize)
    1 folder, 1 computer disk
    Computer disks are restricted. Copies of electronic files may be requested through Access Services: Disk # 2011.genm.43289.0001, Clear Cut Press Core Sample
  - Clear Cut Press (from Series III) (Box 35 Oversize)
  - Wicked Sounds by David Mahler (from Series IV) (Box 35 Oversize)
  - Artwork by James Purdy (from Series IV), 2 (Box 36 Oversize)
  - Artwork by James Purdy (from Series IV), 1993 (Box 37 Broadside)
  - Artwork by James Purdy (from Series IV), 1993 (Box 38 Broadside)
  - Artwork by James Purdy (from Series IV), 1993 (Box 39 Broadside)
- Restricted Fragile
  Box 40 (computer disks): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies of electronic files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  Boxes 41-42 (computer disks and computers): Restricted pending accessioning and preliminary processing.
  - Computer disks, (5 computer disks) (Box 40)
  - Computers (Box 41)
  - Computer disks (Box 42)